here we go. Can you see that? Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Great. Okay. So welcome
to everyone
and everyone who's sort of watching this back. So today we're, we thought we'd
offer some
training on neurodiversity. Actually, this was one that was requested on a
couple of the
feedback forms when we did the feedback it was mentioned. And so recently I
thought about
it again and thought maybe we should just do a little bit of training for
people who
are starting webcam or who have been on webcam for a while and who are neurod
iverse or suspect
they might be. Just to give some tips, some advice, some things to watch out
for and personal
experience as well. And just to open the conversation as well, because we, you
know, we never won
any part of camp or any part of life to be something that we don't talk about
or that
stigmatized. So the more we can open conversations about stuff like this, the
better and make
it a safe space, you know, in the ethical community for us to talk about these
things
as well. And so I called it neurospicy web coming just because I really like
that term.
You know, a lot of people, there's a lot of different terms for neurodiversity.
And I'll
talk a bit more about what what that actually means. But I really like the term
neurospicy
because I think it, it's, it sums me up and many of the amazing neurodiverse
women that
I know is that we're just a little spicy, you know, a little extra, a little
different.
So, so before I get into it, I thought maybe I'll talk a little bit about
myself because
this is actually one thing that, you know, is really dear to my heart and I've
had my
own sort of journey with. So, well, firstly, why talk about neurodiversity? So,
you know,
I've mentioned a couple of things already. It's quite stigmatized. We don't
talk about
it enough. But even if we do talk about it, it can be, you know, there's so
many sort
of TikTok videos and things flying around these days that there's a lot of
misinformation.
You know, a lot of people suspect that there might be neurodiverse, but they
don't really
know. And if they did know, they don't know how that impacts them and their
life and whatever.
So, just to give a bit more information, when it comes to coming, I think it's
great because
whether you've got a diagnosis or not, you might suspect and some of this stuff
might
be really interesting to you and might help you, you know, when it comes to
managing your
business and managing how you can and how it affects you. So, yeah, the reason
that
we're talking about it today is just to raise awareness and to hopefully give,
you know,
whoever watches this back, some insight and some tips on how you might help
yourself to
get the most out of CAM and for it to have a positive impact on your life, if
you're
neurodiverse or think you might be. So, my journey with neurodiversity, so I
always kind
of knew that I was different. I always felt different as a kid. I mean, I was
different
in many ways. I was the only mixed race girl in a white school with like huge
curly hair,
you know. And in a lot of ways, I was very different. I was very quiet. I found
it hard
to connect with people. You know, there was a lot of stuff going on at home. So
, I guess
as I was growing up, I kind of attributed my differences to like my home
environment being
different and it being difficult at home. But the older I got, well, in my late
20s,
or in my 20s, my late 20s, I started studying counselling. So, I decided that I
wanted to
be a counsellor and I started studying counselling and psychotherapy. And part
of studying and
doing all the courses is applying all the theories to yourself and, you know,
do some
deep learning about yourself and your psyche and all the rest of it. And what I
started
to learn was that I was just not taking the same boxes as everyone else. I was
just not
interpreting things in the same way. I was not like moving through the world in
the same
way, you know, experiencing myself in the same way. So, I started to have a lot
of questions
about maybe whether or not I was neurodiverse, what that even meant, maybe I
was like a
bit autistic or, you know, so I started to have a few questions about myself
and noticed
that, you know, I am different and, you know, why is that and how does it
affect me? Then
I, off the back of that, I finished my training, years and years of training.
And it was always
kind of an inkling in the back of my mind, but nothing else too bothered about.
And then
just through chance, I happened to get a job. Well, I applied for this job. I
didn't really
know what it was. It was with disability. It was counselling children and
families and
managing this project due to disability. So, my idea of disability was like
someone in
a wheelchair. I got this job that I was like hugely under qualified form and
realised,
actually know that the disability they were talking about was neuro disability.
It was
largely ADHD, autism, all the other things that we will talk about a bit. And I
began
to work with families. I began to cancel children with disabilities, neurod
iverse kids and young
people and work with their families and educate myself so, so much. I spent a
couple of years
educating myself. All about this and heavily relating to a lot of it and to a
lot of my
younger clients and thinking, "Oh my God, yeah, some of this stuff really makes
sense."
And having a real connection to some of these young people and thinking, "Okay,
I can kind
of see myself in that." So, yeah, off the back of that, a lot of my work now, I
'm in
private practice with psychotherapists and one of my specialisms is neurod
iversity. I now
have a diagnosis of ADD or ADHD now. I also suspect that I might be on the
autistic spectrum.
That's not something that I've gone to get a diagnosis for because I don't at
the moment
feel like I need one, but maybe at some point I'll go and do that. So, that was
my sort of
journey with my own neurodiversity and figuring it out and just noticing that I
was different.
And now, after I've done so much work with it, so much education, I also do
talks and
workshops and all sorts on it, I can see the absolute beauty in it and how
important it
is to get to know yourself and how your neurodiversity might shape the way you
've moved through
the world. So, yeah, so we're bringing this to webcam, we're going to talk a
little bit
more about webcam stuff today. But firstly, to what is neurodiversity? So,
neurodiversity
is a term that refers to the natural differences between people. So, there are
a variety of
differences in people. They influence our experience of the world and ourselves
. So,
the way that we move through the world, the way that we relate to people, even
the sensory
experience that we have can differ largely between individuals. We're all
different.
Neurodiversity is also on a spectrum. So, it's quite difficult because a lot of
people
will say, "Well, I've got this trait or that trait." Yeah, that's true. And
many people,
there's a misconception that it's either am or I'm not something. However, it's
largely
subjective. And even if you were to go for a diagnosis of something, one person
might
say that you do have something and another person might say that you don't. So,
there's
a lot of subjectivity to it. And it's on a spectrum. Even within neurodiversity
groups,
so even within people who are autistic, for example, there's a huge spectrum
and it varies
massively. So, yeah, these, whether or not labels are important is another
conversation,
but just to know that even within the labels, there's so much diversity. So,
some types,
and I won't go into these too much, it's just a touch on it before we talk
about calm
and stuff a bit more. But some of the types of neurodiversity diagnosis that
there are,
so there's ASD, autism, and it's something a little bit more about them here.
You can
read this if you want to. But I don't think we need to go into it too far today
. It's
just giving you an overview. And dyspraxia, probably a lesson in one dyspraxia.
Not many
people know about that. And it's a lot of that is about challenges with
physical coordination.
My son has dyspraxia, and he's just has no, constantly bumping into things.
Coordination
is very difficult. Terats, I'm sure we all know Terats. It's quite one, isn't
it? Dyslexia,
ADHD, dyscal, dyscal, I don't know how you, I can never say that. The one that
involves
numbers. Dyscal, dyscal, you know, we know what we mean. So yeah, they're just
some,
they are just some of the, you know, most well known types of neurodiversity.
There are
lots more, and there are lots of subsections even within those, even within
those. But
it helps, you know, just to have a bit of an understanding of what they are.
And if you
can see any of the traits in yourselves to research them a little bit more. So
challenging
the stigma, this is a big, big thing for me, and something that I'm really
passionate about.
So neurodiversity has long been stigmatised and misunderstood. The overlap
between neurodiversity
and trauma can bring a lot of shame. Yes, it's a universal fact that our genes,
along
with our relational histories, our relationships, and our upbringing are both
factors in the
way that our brain developed. So many traits and diagnosis are passed through
generations
either through genes or through conditioning or both. So sometimes we like, I
see a lot
that people want to say, Oh, it's genetic as a way to, because they feel some
shame about
it not being genetic about it being something to do with their lives. Or, you
know, and I
just think that we just think it's so healthy to move away from that because it
's always,
you know, whether it's genetic or environmental, it doesn't matter. You know,
we are the people
we are. And actually, just being happy and learning to love ourselves and move
through
the world as best we can is the focus, you know, and some difficulties within
neurodiversity
can be overcome with specialised therapy and they put epigenetics in brackets
there because
that's a whole other conversation again. And we'll keep it light today. But you
know, even
when things are genetic, what we now know about epigenetics is that we have
some control
or we have we can adapt. And basically, our we can recondition ourselves so
that our genetics
show up in different ways so that our gene expression can be changed. So even
the things
that we feel are most, you know, intrinsic to do with ourselves, a lot of those
things
can be worked on in therapy. And what we now know about epigenetics is that
even traits
which we get through our genes can change in therapy or under the right
conditions with
an increased sense of safety. And so some difficulties can be overcome. And
some we can
learn to live with some argue that the difficulties many neurodiversity people
face are perfectly
normal adaptation for a healthy person in a toxic society. So I put here in
brackets,
the dysfunction is actually in the world and not in us. I say some argue and I
would
be some, I would be one of those people. You know, I think that's another
conversation
again, but we tend to see, you know, disability as the person has the problem.
But actually,
disability is society is disabling with person. So yeah, that's another
conversation again.
When neurodiversity is discussed, it's usually around disability and
difficulties, but many
neurodiversity people are hugely gifted and can use their diversity to achieve
amazing
things. So many of the most famous artists, scientists, forward thinkers have
been neurodiverse
leaders of change, you know, like Albert Einstein, you know, all the all these
people,
you know, have our neurodiverse and have used their diversity and their
different ways
of seeing the world in order to shape all of our versions of reality. So rather
than it
being seen as something that's holding you back, it's also something that can
be amazing
if it's harnessed. So some of the positives, I wanted to come to the positives
first because
we don't talk about the positives in North. So some of the positive impacts of,
you know,
being a camera and being neurodiverse are masking. So masking, I'm sure most
people
know what that word means, but if you're not familiar with it, it basically
means putting
on a mask, putting on a front, you know, not showing what's underneath. So many
neurodiverse
folk have grown up and gotten really good at masking. So having an outside
persona that
you show the world and having the inside, maybe there's insecurities or some
overwhelm or
some feelings or thoughts which are not really understood in the world and don
't, are not
going to meet your friends or, you know, are going to be difficult in your
environment.
So you get really good holding in your own stuff and on the surface, looking
like, put
it all together or you're fitting in with everyone else. And that's what mask
ing is.
Reading means that many neurodiverse people are incredibly good at reading
environments,
reading other people and showing up in a way that is, you know, adapting to
that environment,
which is an incredible skill to have as a camera because this what we need, you
know,
we can't just show up as one person with every single person and expect, you
know, to engage
and to like connect with them. And actually, what we learn from being so good
at masking
is that we can adapt, we can be a bit of a social chameleon, we can experiment
with
who we are, how we show up, what we show, what we don't. And that's a real
talent that
I think many neurodiverse people have that can really benefit you on cam. You
know, when
you're discovering who you are, what your persona is, how it's comfortable to
show up,
how it's not, you've already kind of done that in life. So it's just an
extension of
that on cam. And for that reason, roleplay can be easier because in many ways,
many of
us have been roleplaying for years, you know, and kind of trying to figure out
who we are
and how we show up. So roleplay can be great. And it can also, for many people,
give, um,
be a safety net on cam, because roleplay gives you a set of instructions, um,
which you
can play with, hide behind, you know, you use as a safety net. So roleplay is
often, you
know, a talent for neurodiverse people on cam, um, increased creativity. So
many people
and I've worked as a therapist, a psychotherapist now for six, seven years,
largely with people
neurodiverse people. Um, and so I've learned and seen firsthand that for many
people, their
brains are not organised in the same way. And the way that they see the world
is not, is
not the state is not always the same. So many, there's a pre conception, um,
that that means
that neurodiverse folk have like a reduced capacity or a reduced, um, way of
seeing the
world. But actually, I would say the opposite is true. It's an increased
capacity. It's
that you can see more than what the average person can see. Um, which also
means that
you can think outside the box. Um, you can be over minded. You have a capacity
for increased
creativity. Um, of course, everyone's unique and everyone's different within
this, but
on the whole, um, if your brain is wired differently, it often means that it's
open
to more than the average person, which is amazing when it comes to cam, because
you
can experiment, you can be creative, you can think about an outfit's in a
different way,
or, you know, how you want to show up aesthetically or like the nuances in your
character, you know,
you can really play into that creativity when it comes to cam. Energy, energy
is a big one.
And obviously can also be a struggle as well, because, you know, we'll talk
about it, but
overwhelm and stuff like that. But a lot of neurodiverse people, when they're
having fun and
enjoying themselves and in the right environment can have, can be quite high
energy. And that's
great for cam. Like a lot of people, they want to come into your room for an
experience, a connection,
you know, they're coming to, you know, to feel seen and to connect with you and
to share with
you their fantasies and have some fun. And so energy is what they need, isn't
it? Like,
you know, some energy to welcome them into, for you to be excited and happy to
be there.
And it's amazing for your clients and we'll have them coming back and back. So
using the energy
that you've got can be really beneficial. And of course, uniqueness, you know,
we talk so often
about, you know, there are lots of agencies out there who have like a, they
make the girls' profiles
as a standard, just they say the same thing, they look largely the same, their
photos are the same,
you know, it's all set around what we think men want. But it's so, it's so, it
's all the same,
you know, it doesn't stand out at all. So, you know, part of your neurod
iversity may be that
your differences make you unique and give you a unique selling point. They give
you things about
you which are really interesting and diverse and that you can, you can
capitalize on when you're
making your profile and when you're chatting to your clients and building
connections and so
celebrating your uniqueness can really help when it comes to coming in.
So potential difficulties then, and chatting a bit about each of these, so
fatigue. So, of course,
if you're masking, if you're, you know, going through the world and it's taking
you a lot more
energy than it is the average person to think about how much eye contact you're
giving someone
or what it is you're going to say next in the conversation or maybe you're
trying to manage
yourself so that you don't interrupt people all the time which can be, you know
, a common thing to
struggle with. There are so many reasons why you have to, you might have an
extra level of having
to manage yourself and these can lead to fatigue. So, you know, what a task
which may take, you know,
neurotypical person five minutes might take you all day and the fatigue that
comes with that
is something to be aware of, you know, knowing your limits, knowing what can,
that what the things that you can do with very minimal effort and the things
that are going to
take a lot of effort and a lot of, you know, energy from you is really
important because,
you know, in the mainstream society, we, we all hold ideas about what's a quick
five minute task
and what's a big task, but that might be the completely the opposite way around
for you.
It may be totally different. So, knowing yourself and knowing the tasks that
will take a lot of energy
from you and drain you and the things that you can do really easily is
important and not just being
led by other people's ideas of what that is because it might be really
different for you.
And so, managing your fatigue on PAM is just knowing, just knowing yourself,
giving yourself
enough time, giving yourself enough breaks if you need to, knowing the things
that are going to
really wear you out. I mean, the next point on that is sensory issues and that
and that is a point
with fatigue as well. So, many neurodiverse people experience their body in a
slightly different way
to a neurodiver person. So, that might mean if you're wearing anything tight or
restrictive,
anything with labels or buttons, you know, they can be rubbing your skin and
irritating you and,
you know, just having a negative impact on you semantically. So, little things
like that can
really add to your fatigue and your overwhelm. So, knowing, you know, what it
is, what sensory
things are an issue for you. For instance, if you're using a ring light, but
you are light
sensitive and you may not even know it so far, you may be just that each time
you're on cam,
you put your ring light on the highest setting and then, you know, you get a
headache after the first
half an hour or something, just tuning into your environment, your sensory
environment and thinking
about times when you're overwhelmed or you're in pain or, you know, you're
irritable, just check in
with the environment around you. What am I wearing? What's the lighting like?
Are there sounds? Are
there distractions around? Is there a lot going on? You know, just being aware
of any potential
sensory issues and, you know, you can google it. You can google neurodiversity
and sensory issues
and get an idea of what some of the things might be that you can look out for
and help you to adapt
to those things. Well, thank you for sharing. I was just looking at the message
. Yes,
special is it? So, I have sensory issues and now I'm aware of it. Yeah, amazing
. So many people are
not aware of it for such a long time and the first project that I worked on was
working with children
and in the school environment, there'd be a child that was really destructive
and it was
literally something as small as they were sitting next to the radiator every
day and it was humming
and, you know, they were just massively overstimulated and just changing that
one small thing about
where they were sitting completely changed who they were and how they could
turn up in school. So,
yes, little things to do with sensory input can be so important. So, it's
definitely worth thinking
about when you're on cam and in life. And organization and planning. So, this
can be difficult.
Organization and planning can either be a strong point of yours as a neurod
iverse person and you've
absolutely got it down and you're amazing at it or it could be incredibly
difficult.
Now, for me, it's incredibly difficult. I have this cam business, it's a lovely
Georgia. I also
have my psychotherapy business and I'm a mum. I have a lot to manage, I have a
lot and so
it's extremely difficult for me to organise and plan. So, I have to have a
diary, a monthly
diary, a weekly diary, a daily list. You know, I have to be really consistent
with myself about
the lists that I have and what I'm looking at each day and my prompts, I even
have like little
posters to prompt me to look at my list and stuff like that. So, it can be
difficult and this can,
this can, you know, impact our camming because of course it's a business, isn't
it? You want to be
regularly getting on cam, so you've got those regulars building up and you're
building up your
money. You want to be, you know, thinking about what hours and times you're
going to come on,
replying to people, doing the admin tasks around webcam, which, if you're
anything like me, can
be really difficult. And so, yeah, just being aware of it, you know, making
lists or doing
whatever it is you can. You know, some people find that if they've got music on
, for example,
while they're replying to the messages or doing some admin that that can help
them,
or, you know, just thinking outside of the box of ways that you can help
yourself with the planning
and organization and not shaming yourself that if it's difficult for you,
because it's not laziness
at all and that's, you know, a message many of us have been given over the
years from caregivers
or society, is that if we can't do something, it's because we're lazy. No, if
we can't do something,
if we, you know, if we get that block, which I'm sure many of us neurodiverse
that will know when
you've just got one task, you know, like taking something to the post office
for me to return it
is like such a mama thing. I can't even explain how difficult that is for me,
which is crazy. And,
you know, when people think about my life and all the stuff I do and all the
things I'm managing,
they just find that hard to believe that that is so difficult for me. But yeah,
just not shaming
yourself about the things you find difficult is important. And if you can,
being open and honest
with the people that you're around about what your difficulties are, you know,
I know Georgia and
I work together and we work in very different ways, Georgia is amazing at the
stuff behind the scenes.
She's a very good at organization. She's very good at doing a process. She's
very good at honing
in on a process. I'm absolutely rubbish at it. I'm very, very good at being
creative and, you know,
speaking and lots of other things, but organization and getting into the
details of a process
is not, is not my strong point. I find really hard. And that is a conversation,
you know, that I do
have and have had with Georgia. So, and it's a conversation you can have with
your mentor
around coming, you know, just let them know what it is that you find difficult.
If there's some
shame there, just, you know, try and feel compassionate towards yourself, maybe
even share that you're
feeling a bit shameful about it. And I'm sure your mentor will do whatever they
can to put you at ease
and to help you with it. Pacing, so pacing, you know, I was talking about
energy on the last slide
as, you know, a real positive. It can also be a difficulty because if you're
really high energy,
then you might be really, really quick. And then it's hard for your clients to
keep up with you.
So just checking in with your pace, allowing yourself to just slow down a
little bit
sometimes can help you to engage a bit more fully with clients. And also, you
know, pacing is in
some days you may be really, really quick and really, really high energy and
getting low
certain other days really, really slow and really, you know, so just giving
yourself permission to
check in with however you're feeling that day and it's okay, you know, just
making can work for you.
Maybe in the days when you're really on it, you're really on top of it, you
want to have a certain
persona. And in the other days, maybe you could be a bit more dumb because it's
okay to be slow
and controlled and, you know, when you're, when you're dumbing. So just being
aware of your pacing
and not shaming yourself, just using it to your advantage. Memory recall, so
memory recall can be
hard for many neurodiverse people. And recalling little details like names and,
you know, specific
details about clients might be quite difficult. So, you know, again, writing
things down, having a
different way to remember things can be quite important. And again, not shaming
yourself,
just finding ways to deal with it, just finding ways around it. Perfectionism.
So, perfectionism
is something that many neurodiverse people struggle with, you know, whether it
's because
they've always felt different, and they've always felt a bit ashamed, or, you
know, they've always
had a level of shame about themselves, or whether it's low self worth, or just
sometimes when you
know you have so much potential, because you have quite a complex mind, but it
's difficult to reach
that potential because there are a lot of barriers in the way, whether it's
fatigue or
organization or whatever, then perfectionism can be a really, a real struggle.
It can be really,
really hard. And so, just again, giving yourself permission that nobody knows
what they're doing,
nobody's got it perfectly down. Even those of us who've been on par for many
years and are really
comfortable with it, we're not going to keep every client, you know, and we're
not going to do
everything perfectly every time. There's no such thing. So, just giving
yourself a mission
to check out of that perfectionism, if you can, just remind yourself that, you
know, we're all
imperfect humans, we'll just do the best we can. So, managing RSD, I wanted to
put this one in,
because it's such a big one. So, RSD is, it stands for rejection sensitivity
disorder,
which I hate that, I hate that phrase, because anything that's labelled as a
disorder, I really
don't like. However, it's important to talk about it, because it's something
that many people,
and ADHD and autism as well, can experience, and that you can make things
really difficult. So,
rejection sensitivity disorder is when you are always anticipating that you're
going to be rejected.
So, it's this feeling of inadequacy. And, you know, when you're talking to
people, when you're
interacting with people, it's this real being on high alert that they're going
to find out,
that you're doing it wrong, or they're going to judge you, they're going to
criticize you,
they're going to reject you. And, it can be a real struggle for some people to
cope with.
The reason why I put that in there with consent is because this is something
that I'm really
passionate about, that, you know, because of RSD, and not just RSD, there are
many other reasons,
you know, trauma, our society, the patriarchy, there are many reasons why women
sometimes find
it hard to say what we want for what we mean, or hold our boundaries, because
we're worried about
the other person rejecting or criticizing us, or getting something wrong. Well,
this can be,
these can be symptoms of RSD, and when you're doing something which involves
maybe being sexually
explicit, or even just talking about fantasies and sexual stuff, you really
need to be aware
of your capacity to give consent. So, just noticing it's something to think
about and notice within
yourself, if, you know, maybe you might like to look up RSD and see what it is,
and whether you
relate to it or not. And if you do, just really thinking about, okay, how can I
centre my needs,
and my safety, and my consent giving on cam, rather than centering the other
person's experience,
and what they're going to think of me, and whether or not I'm going to be
rejected, if I'm doing it
wrong, it doesn't matter. What matters is, the first thing that matters is that
you are safe,
and that you can trust yourself. The last thing on the list there is self-trust
, and I think RSD
can really get in the way of self-trust, because if we are putting other people
's needs and feeling
ahead of our own safety, that's a bit of the rest of the stuff there is in it.
So, giving yourself
permission not to consent to something, even if it's the thing that you do,
even if it's, you know,
oh, I always do that. Well, no, there might be one point that you don't do it
with, and that's okay,
because the energy's off, or you don't feel like it, or whatever, you don't
even need a reason.
So, giving yourself permission to remove your consent at any time, to be
upfront about what
it is that you do, and what you don't, and just taking note that if you do have
RSD, or if you
relate to some of those traits, it's okay, you know, just holding yourself
through that, and almost
parenting yourself through that, you know, being a kind, compassionate leader
towards yourself,
and being aware of it. So yeah, those are the potential difficulties. Does
anyone have any of
it, sort of, difficulties, or other things that they might add to that list?
You can let me know
in the chat if you want to, and maybe I'll just, I'll think about them, or chat
about them.
Making webcam work for you, so just to sum up some of the things that we've
said, and just
some things to remember about making webcam work for you, if you're neurodivist
. So, getting to know
yourself, so a lot of the things on the previous couple of pages, you can just
look through and
be curious about yourself, you know. What are your traits? What are your
triggers? What are the things
that overwhelm you? Which days do you feel your best, and what's happening then
? How can you tune
into that? So, getting to know yourself, and you can use, like, the different
labels of neurodiversity,
and look through the traits and things in order to, like, think whether that's
you or not,
but don't hold yourself to them too tightly. Even if you have a diagnosis of
something, you can be
unique within that. You don't have to sit perfectly with it. So, being curious
about you, and what
matters to you, what makes you tick, what makes you tired, what excites you,
the more you know yourself,
the more you can look after yourself. So, getting to know yourself is really
important.
Accountability versus shame. So, you know, this is often something which ties
into the work that
I do with neurodiversity, but not just with anyone, with absolutely anyone, but
RSD and things like
that can tie into this. So, you know, we can be accountable for ourselves the
things we're doing
and saying, how we're showing up, how hard we're working, you know, but we don
't need shame in
order to do that. And many of us have been taught through society or through
parents or whoever,
but we need to shame ourselves into action. But if we're not doing something,
then we must be like,
oh, for God's sake, you know, just, you know, we criticize ourselves into
action. We don't need
to. We don't need to do that. You know, that's kind of a toxic story that we
need shame in
order to do something good with our lives. What we need is pride and love. They
're the only things
that we need in order to achieve and move forward. So, maybe noticing the
things in your life that
you struggle with and whether or not you're shaming yourself, trying to shame
yourself out of doing
them and maybe moving away from shame a little bit more towards pride. Who is
it that I want to be
and how can I meet my own needs so that I can get there? Not how can I suppress
or reject my own
needs? No, how can I meet them? Even if they don't look like what everyone else
is doing, it might be
that you need something different and that's okay, you know. And acknowledging
the benefits,
so acknowledging the benefits of webcam, I mean, I could have just put
gratitude in that in that
bit. The webcam is just amazing for so many reasons. You know, it's a job where
as a neurodiverse
person, you can turn up to work whatever time you want. You can work for as
long as you can
and then stop. You can have breaks whenever you want. You know, you can turn up
with whatever energy
you've got on whatever day and be a different person. You don't need to be, you
know, talking to,
you don't need to be holding eye contact with people all the time. You don't
need to be
dressing a certain way. You don't need to be conforming, you know, as much as
you would. If you were in a
nine to five job and had to drag yourself out of bed every day and be told,
like, when you can have
a break and when you're going home, you can manage your own life and your own
self. And so
acknowledging the benefits of that, it just helps you be so much more grateful
to cam. And it helps
you put more energy and, you know, action into it because if the alternative to
cam is going and
working for someone else and, you know, who's not going to understand your
needs and who is
going to make it difficult, then we can just be super super super grateful for
cam. And I think
that every day, you know, cam is the reason why I was able to, you know, pay
through my education
and support myself and my kids in order to do the things that I want to do. And
it's amazing. And
at the same time, you know, not being jobs where just my strengths are not
realised and my weaknesses
are, you know, used against me. So yeah, that will never happen with, with us
at least in this
community, it will never happen. So we can all be so grateful for that. And
recognise that,
because sometimes we spend so much time thinking about ourselves, don't we?
Like, am I doing things
right? Have I got something wrong? Am I saying the right thing? Am I sexy? Like
,
recognizing your clients are unique as well, you know, you might have some form
of neurodiversity
or difference or whatever. And so might your clients, you know, it's, we
sometimes judge ourselves by
this standard of normal, but what is normal? And it's likely that probably a
large percentage of
your clients in neurodiversity as well, because they've stepped outside the box
of what is normal,
you know. And so, yeah, acknowledging that your clients are also unique. And so
not having to hide
your uniqueness, actually, maybe it's something that you can connect with them
about. Because I
know I have done for sure. And I suppose that leads to the last point, really,
which is embracing
and capitalizing on your differences. You know, the more you can embrace about
yourself, the more
you can be authentic, the more you can be playful and creative, you know, you
can capitalize on
those things that make you, you know. And when somebody gets on cam gets a real
feel for their
actual you, that is like, I don't know, messy and authentic and fun and
exciting. And, you know,
that gives them so much to, so much more to work with, isn't it? It just makes
them get to want to
know, you know, makes them intrigued and interested in you. And, and means that
maybe they can be
unique as well, they can, they can show themselves to you as well. So, yeah,
getting to know yourself,
so knowing, you know, your sensory stuff, your, what's going on in your mind,
you,
all the things that we talked about going to know yourself and how you might
meet your needs better.
Meeting your needs with pride and love and not through shame. And acknowledging
the benefits
and, and being grateful, practising gratitude towards cam in this community,
acknowledging your clients are unique as well. And, yeah, embracing and capital
izing on your
differences, because they're amazing. And there's so, so many amazing things
about being no adverse.
And there we are. There we have it. And that was a lot of talking by me.
Normally, I'm used to
me and Georgia doing these together. So, that fun is used for all my talking.
But I hope that it's
been, you know, I hope that it's been helpful. And just know that I'm here, if
anybody wants to
reach out in the group or whatever I do lead an extremely busy life, but I will
get back to you
as soon as I can. And also your mentor, you can reach out to your mentor about
these things as well.
And yeah, have a conversation, start a conversation in the group. If you've got
a question or there's
something that you want to know or you want to talk about or you want to
highlight, just know that,
you know, the WhatsApp groups, that's what they're there for. And everyone is
really welcoming and
loving. And so, if you've ever got something that you want to mention, then
mention it to me,
mention it to your mentor or in the chat, you know, whatever works for you and
we're here.
Okay. Everybody. Well, thank you so much. Thank you for coming. Especially in
the daytime,
we were experimenting with having this in the daytime. So yeah, we're just
experimenting with
doing calls at different times. I appreciate you taking time out of your day to
come to the call.
And good luck with Cam, if you're going on. And we'll see you very soon.
Thanks so much. Thank you so much. Just one question, if I may ask,
neurodiversity connected with being a highly sensitive person.
Yes. Absolutely. Yeah. You know, there was somebody that described it as having
a layer of
skin removed so that everything feels more, you know, like emotionally but
physically as well.
Yeah, absolutely. It's definitely linked with that. And there's a lot of
research on that.
Yeah, which means, you know, it makes it so important to know the things that
you're sensitive
about, doesn't it? I think especially when you're working. Yes, for everyday
functioning and
organizing, because it's not just like, I've always always thought like, all
being a highly
sensitive person means like you're so emotional. No, it comes down to, as we
mentioned, so many
different things and aspects and facets of a person, the way a person thinks or
reacts or even
acknowledges certain things. The way the mind brain functions, it's maybe a bit
different or
complex, but it's good to know. It's good to know. Yeah, I think, yeah, it's
good to know, and it's
good to know, you know, it's good to know that all our brains work differently.
And I think,
I think for many people with the sensitivity, a client once described it to me,
like, you know,
it's like an office where like most people have an open office space and there
's loads of little
offices in that. There's like, everyone's like cornered off and got their own
little closed
door office. And that's how their mind works. All these sections, it's like
family work,
all these different sections of stuff. But then he was like, my mind is like an
open plan office,
and everyone's just in there together. Like, my family work, what's going on in
the world,
this, that it's all just in the same big space. So like, sorting through it all
, it's like, God,
I can't forget about the genocide in the world in order to go to work, because
it's like all in
the same bit, you know, and it can be overwhelming sometimes. Yes. Yeah, yeah,
absolutely. And
sometimes we have, it's like this stigma, or I want a feeling that we cannot
share some things
like with someone, because maybe people won't understand or judge, you know,
like just brush it
off, don't think that much, you're over. And the common thing is, or labeling
is,
you're just thinking too much. It's not just that. It's more complex. Yeah,
yeah, I mean,
you could counteract that by saying you're not thinking enough. I love that.
Yeah, that's true. That's true to many people. They just don't think for
starters,
not let alone enough. I love that. Thank you, this is a wonderful call. Girls,
I enjoyed listening
to you and seeing you. It's like a ceiling for the soul. That's lovely. Thank
you so much.
Thank you for your comments as well. It's really lovely. Thank you for your
energy.
Much appreciated. Yes, I'll see. I'll see you girls very soon. Have a lovely
day.
Thanks, Ralph. Bye. Bye girls.